{"tossups": [{"question": "An editor who spoke for this group opined that one president was \"Fungus from the corrupt womb of bigotry and fanaticism.\" Soldiers clashed with this group in the 1864 Charleston Riot in Illinois. George E. Pugh was an Ohio senator from this group, as was Congressman Alexander Long. Order Number 38 was used to punish members of this group including Lambdin Milligan and Clement Vallandigham, both part of the Knights of the Golden Circle. For ten points, name this group of \"Peace Democrats\" who opposed the Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Copperhead</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Peace Democrat</u></b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A member of this organization named Trifko Grabe\u017e [[GRAH-besh]] was spared the death penalty because of his age. This organization, referred to as \"Unification or Death,\" was established by Colonel Dragutin Dimitrijevi\u0107 [[drah-GOO-tin dee-mee-tree-YEH-vitch]], also known as Apis [[AH-peess]], who was executed on charges of treason in 1917. In 1903, this organization's founder carried out the May Coup, which culminated in the deaths of King Alexander and Queen Draga of Serbia. For ten points, name this organization responsible for planning the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand.", "answer": "The <b><u>Black Hand</u></b> (accept <b><u>Crna ruka</u></b>; accept <b><u>Unification or Death</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the <em>Periplus of the Erythraean Sea</em>, this island was referred to as \u201cof the Dioscuri.\u201d After the Battle of Barawa, Trist\u00e3o da Cunha [[KOON-yah]] re-grouped his forces on this island, where the Mahra sultans ruled. Traders passed through the Guardafui Channel en route to this island, which is home to a tree named for its resemblance to dragon\u2019s blood. The British ended their attempts to acquire this island following the capture of nearby Aden. For ten points, name this Yemeni island off the Arabian Peninsula.", "answer": "<b><u>Socotra</u></b> (or <b><u>Suqu\u1e6dr\u0101</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author examined Robert Foster\u2019s path to becoming a physician and Ida Gladney\u2019s departure from a life of sharecropping in a 2010 book. In a 2020 book, this author lists \u201cdivine will\u201d and \u201cendogamy\u201d as two of the eight pillars of the titular concept. This one-time editor-in-chief of the Howard University newspaper studied the Great Migration in her book <em>The Warmth of Other Suns</em>. Social stratification in America is compared to the caste system in a book by, for ten points, what Pulitzer Prize-winning African-American journalist?", "answer": "Isabel <b><u>Wilkerson</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "Many stories from this tribe\u2019s oral tradition were preserved by its member John Joseph Mathews. Mollie Kyle and her family were among the members of this tribe affected in a campaign carried out by William Hale, who was sentenced to life in prison for a series of crimes against them. David Grann\u2019s book <em>Killers of the Flower Moon</em> examines the violent attempts to profit from the oil deposits belonging to this tribe. For ten points, name this Great Plains tribe which shares its name with an Oklahoma county.", "answer": "<b><u>Osage</u></b> Nation (accept <b><u>Ni-u-kon-ska</u></b>; prompt on \u201cPeople of the Muddy Waters\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An incident that inspired this song led Adrian Perkins to offer its singer an apology in 2019. Ren\u00e9 Hall arranged this song, which appears on the album <em>Ain\u2019t That Good News</em>. The singer of this work claimed to have been inspired by \u201cBlowin\u2019 in the Wind\u201d and wrote this song after an incident in which he was refused a room at a motel in Shreveport, Louisiana. The refrain, \u201cIt's been a long time comin', but I know\u201d appears in this 1964 song which Jennifer Hudson sang at the 2020 Democratic convention. For ten points, name this Civil Rights-era song written by Sam Cooke.", "answer": "\"A <b><u>Change is Gonna Come\"</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man was killed by the daughter of Cocalus [[koh-KAH-luhs]] when she poured boiling water over him, after which this man became a judge of the dead. While ruling from Knossos, this man is said to have received direct instruction from his father, Zeus, on what laws to enforce against his people. Arthur Evans took this man's name for a civilization which used the Linear A writing system. Every nine years, this man sent fourteen Athenian boys and girls to his labyrinth to be eaten by a bull-headed man. For ten points, name this ancient king of Crete.", "answer": "King <b><u>Minos</u></b> (prompt on \"Minoan\"; prompt on \"Minotaur\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "One leader of this dynasty was killed at a battle in which his opponents built a thorned <em>zariba</em> fence around the city of Gallabat. Though initially establishing \"tent governments,\" this dynasty founded a capital at the city of Gondar. Yekuno Amlak, like other rulers of this dynasty, was given the title \u201cLion of Judah.\u201d Claiming descent from the Queen of Sheba, this dynasty was led by a ruler worshipped by the Rastafari movement. Haile Selassie [[HAI-luh seh-LAH-see]] ruled, for ten points, what Ethiopian dynasty named for a biblical king?", "answer": "<b><u>Solomon</u></b>ic Dynasty (accept House of <b><u>Solomon</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Historian Gwynne Dyer compared this battle to a \"fully loaded 747 crashing\u2026every 5 minutes for 8 hours.\" Pyotr Bagration [[pee-OH-ter bah-GRAY-tee-OHN]] helped set up lunettes and redans at this battle. Fleches were set up by Barclay de Tolly at the Kolocha [[koh-LOH-chah]] stream in this battle, which included a charge on the Raevsky Redoubt. Mikhail Kutuzov replaced a commander for Tsar Alexander I at this battle. For ten points, name this 1812 pyrrhic victory for Napoleon Bonaparte, after which he occupied Moscow.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Borodino</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man travelled with John Clarke to England in an attempt to get William Coddington's commission revoked. This man wrote <em>A Key into the Language of America</em>, the first-published English-language study of Native American languages. After writing a tract criticizing King James for stealing land from the Narragansett, this man moved to Salem and served as an assistant to Samuel Skelton. Providence Plantations was founded by, for ten points, what man who, after being expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony, founded Rhode Island?", "answer": "Roger <b><u>Williams</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In Britain, this period was marked by the creation of the Fetter Lane Society and one man's Aldersgate experience. A leader during this period created the Bethesda Orphanage in Georgia. During this period, books and clothes were burned by James Davenport, and William Tennent formed the Log College. Dartmouth, Yale, and Princeton were formed during this religious era, in which the Northampton Revival occurred. George Whitefield [[WIT-field]] was a leader during, for ten points, what religious revival in the mid-18th century?", "answer": "<b><u>First Great Awakening</u></b> (accept <b><u>Evangelical Revival</u></b>; prompt on \"Great Awakening\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Arthur Rostron was captain of this vessel, which made its maiden voyage to Boston from Liverpool in 1903. After sending traffic from Cape Cod, Harold Cottam received a message while serving on this vessel which prompted it to cut off hot water usage in order to save steam from the engines so it could cover 58 nautical miles as quickly as possible. That effort occurred when, after midnight on April 15, 1912, this vessel received a distress signal indicating that a ship had hit an iceberg. For ten points, name this ship which rescued survivors from the <em>Titanic</em>.", "answer": "RMS <em><b><u>Carpathia</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s book <em>On Self-Pollution</em> advocated for abstinence. The 1829-1851 cholera epidemic popularized the teachings of this man, who founded the American Physiological Society as part of his advocacy of \u201cnatural hygiene.\u201d This man called for the avoidance of aluminum and chlorine additives in white bread, instead advocating for bread made with home-milled flour. Considered the \u201cfather of vegetarianism,\u201d for ten points, what advocate of simple foods pioneered a namesake cracker?", "answer": "Sylvester <b><u>Graham</u></b> (accept <b><u>Graham</u></b> Cracker)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "This modern country is home to Africa's oldest mosque, the Mosque of the Companions, and much of its territory was once ruled by the Bajag and Medri Bahri kingdoms. When it was still an Italian colony, a 71-kilometer cableway crossed what is now this country to reach the base of the Red Sea Flotilla, which was scuttled until Edward Ellsberg raised the ships at Massawa. In Operation Fenkil, this country was targeted by Mengistu of Ethiopia. With a capital known as \"Little Rome,\" for ten points, what is this East African country, officially independent since 1993?", "answer": "State of <b><u>Eritrea</u></b> (accept Italian <b><u>Eritrea</u></b>; prompt on \"Italian East Africa\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The board of this institution was first presided over by Claudius Crozet, a civil engineer who sought to model it partly on the <em>\u00c9cole Polytechnique</em>. James Lane graduated from this institution, whose first superintendent, Francis Henney Smith, previously taught at Hampden-Sydney College. Students of this institution participated in the Battle of New Market, and this institution was created in Lexington from the remnants of a state arsenal. \u201cStonewall\u201d Jackson taught at this institution, whose cadets were relocated in 1864 to Richmond. For ten points, name this state military academy.", "answer": "<b><u>Virginia Military Institute</u></b> (accept <b><u>VMI</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This Supreme Court justice, a nominee of George H.W. Bush, recused himself from the case as his son, Jamal, was a senior cadet at VMI at the time.", "answer": "Clarence <b><u>Thomas</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Agent Orange was first deployed during this event, in which Sir Gerald Templer implemented a system of internment camps known as \"new villages\" as part of the Briggs' Plan. This event included the Batang Kali massacre, in which 24 unarmed villagers were killed by British troops, known as \"Britain's My Lai [[mee-LAI]].\" One side which fought in this event was known as the MNLA and was led by Chin Peng. For ten points, name this guerilla war fought in a Southeast Asian country from 1948 to 1960 between pro-independence Communists and the British Empire.", "answer": "The <b><u>Malaya</u></b>n <b><u>Emergency</u></b> (accept <b><u>Darurat Malaya</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "J. Howard Miller incorporated this phrase into one work, which inspired a street artist named Phoenix to use it in another work commemorating the election of Julia Gillard as prime minister of Australia. This four-word phrase was popularized in a campaign run by Westinghouse Electric\u2019s War Production Coordinating Committee. This phrase appears in a blue speech bubble above a woman who flexes her arm and wears a red bandana. For ten points, name this motivational phrase found above Rosie the Riveter on U.S. World War Two posters.", "answer": "<b><u>\"We Can Do It!\"</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Garnier de l\u2019Aube [[gahr-NYEH duh LOHB]] once claimed that the \u201cblood of\u201d this man \u201cchoked\u201d another man into inaction. This man gave a speech in which he claimed, \u201cTo conquer them we must dare, dare again, always dare.\u201d That speech by this subject of a play of Georg B\u00fcchner [[BYOOK-nuh] was thought to have contributed to the September Massacres. En route to his execution, this man\u2019s last words were, \"My only regret is that I am going before that rat, Robespierre.\" The first head of the Committee of Public Safety, for ten points, who was this early leader of the French Revolution?", "answer": "Georges <b><u>Danton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A \u201cDeclaration of Principles\u201d outlining the aims of this group was partly</u></b> <b><u>written by its co-founder, Monroe Trotter. Members of this group lobbied critics in</u></b> <b><u>Chicago to ignore a play titled</u> </b><em><b><u>The Clansman</u></b></em><b><u>. Following the Springfield Race Riot of</u></b> <b><u>1908, members of this group joined with white activists to form the (+)</u> NAACP. Allegedly named for the \u201cmighty current\u201d of change it aspired to achieve, this movement was founded in 1905 by a group including (*) </b>W.E.B. Dubois [[doo-BOYSS]]. For ten points, name this civil rights organization named for a New York-Ontario waterway near where it first met.", "answer": "<b><u>Niagara</u></b> Movement (prompt on \"NM\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 1956 reform named for either this man or Evsei Liberman focused on</u></b> <b><u>profitability and included an article titled \"For All and For Oneself.\" This man</u></b> <b><u>mediated the Tashkent Agreement between India and Pakistan in 1966 and managed</u></b> <b><u>1973 and 1979 economic reforms to counter the Era of (+)</u> Stagnation. Lyndon Johnson and this man met at the Glassboro Summit, leading up to the Moscow Treaty with (*) </b>West Germany and the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this Soviet statesman who served as premier alongside First Secretary Leonid Brezhnev from 1964 to 1980.", "answer": "Alexei <b><u>Kosygin</u></b> (accept <b><u>Kosygin</u></b> reform)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A cameo on this show was the answer to the winning question for the first</u></b> <b><u>million-dollar winner of the U.S. version of</u> </b><em><b><u>Who Want\u2019s to Be a Millionaire</u></b></em><b><u>, John</u></b> <b><u>Carpenter. On this show, Judy Carne said \u201cIt may be rice wine to you, but it's still (+)</u></b> <b>sake [[SAH-keh]] to me.\u201d Running from 1968 to 1973, this show was the most popular T.V. show in America in its first three seasons. Richard Nixon appeared in a cameo on this show during which he said its catchphrase (*) </b>\u201csock it to me.\u201d For ten points, name this sketch comedy show co-hosted by Dan Rowan and Dick Martin.", "answer": "<em>Rowan and Martin's</em> <em><b><u>Laugh-In</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>The apportionment of land brought about by this treaty prompted one ethnic</u></b> <b><u>group to organize the League of Prizren. Nicholas Ignatiev helped negotiate this</u></b> <b><u>treaty, which was partly reversed by the Treaty of Berlin. This treaty is</u></b> <b><u>commemorated on Liberation Day in (+)</u> Bulgaria. An independent Romania was created via this agreement, which also established the Kosovo Vilayet. Bringing an end to an (*) </b>1877-1878 war between Russia and a western neighbor, for ten points, what is this treaty which restructured Ottoman holdings in the Balkans?", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>San Stefano</u></b> (accept Peace of <b><u>San Stefano</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ayastefanos</u> </b>Antla\u015fmas\u0131; accept <b><u>Ayastefanos</u></b> Muahedesi)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A work by this man was printed unbound in prints of five every month to</u></b> <b><u>avoid depositing to British libraries. Joseph Mason painted backgrounds for this</u></b> <b><u>man's best known work, which was printed as the \"Double Elephant Folio.\" Scientists</u></b> <b><u>doubt this man's (+)</u> banding experiment for having a 40 percent rate of return. Specimens depicted by this man were sent to him from Nathaniel Jarvis Wyeth's expedition and feature extinct (*) </b>birds such as the passenger pigeon. For ten points, name this French-American ornithologist who published <em>The Birds of America</em>.", "answer": "John James <b><u>Audubon</u></b> (accept Jean-Jacques <b><u>Rabin</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this offensive, which began with the Battle of Amiens, the Allies</u></b> <b><u>managed to break through the Hindenburg line after the Battle of St. Quentin Canal.</u></b> <b><u>This event reversed (+)</u> German gains made during the Spring Offensive and forced them to retreat behind the Rhine. The last soldier to die during this offensive was Henry (*) </b>Gunther, who charged a German roadblock and was shot dead one minute before an armistice went into effect. For ten points, name this series of Allied offensives which ended World War One.", "answer": "<b><u>Hundred Days</u></b> Offensive (or <b><u>Grand</u></b> Offensive)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Moore v. Dempsey</u></b></em><b><u> vacated the death sentences of six people involved in this</u></b> <b><u>event. Prior to this event, Robert L. Hill organized a meeting of the Progressive</u></b> <b><u>Farmers and Household Union of America at Hoop Spur at which two (+)</u> white deputies arrived and exchanged shots. The NAACP sent Walter F. White to investigate this 1919 event, in which Governor Charles Brough requested Federal troops to put down a \"Black insurrection\" in (*) </b>Phillips County. For ten points, name this massacre of Black farmworkers in Arkansas, the bloodiest racial conflict in U.S. history.", "answer": "<b><u>Elaine</u></b> massacre (accept <b><u>Elaine</u></b> race riot)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>German U-boats sank twenty merchant ships during a battle named for this</u></b> <b><u>river that involved fighting at the Strait of Belle Isle. On June 26th, 1959, Queen</u></b> <b><u>Elizabeth II and (+)</u> Dwight D. Eisenhower attended the official opening of a waterway connecting this body of water to a larger one. In 1535, (*) </b>Jacques Cartier [[kar-TYEH]] became the first European explorer to traverse this river, which he named after the feast day of a martyred Catholic deacon. For ten points, name this river which forms part of the international boundary between Canada and the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>St. Lawrence</u></b> River (accept Battle of the <b><u>St. Lawrence</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Backers of this man were identified by the University of Bristol project as</u></b> <b><u>Father Giovanni Antonio de Carbonarris and the Bardi Family. This man's supporter,</u></b> <b><u>William Weston, likely led the first (+)</u> Northwest Passage expedition. This man searched for Hy-Brasil, and this man's \"John Day letter\" recorded his first voyage. In his second voyage, this man found Cape Bonavista and St. (*) </b>John's while sailing the <em>Matthew</em>. For ten points, name this Italian who explored the coast of Newfoundland for Henry VII of England.", "answer": "John <b><u>Cabot</u></b> (accept Giovanni <b><u>Caboto</u></b>; accept Zuan <b><u>Cabotto</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}